{"tossups": [{"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable Though beginning tolerantly, within 80 years of the start of this process, a successor to those who carried it out reportedly said, \u201cMilk [those affected by this process] and once their milk dries, suck their blood.\u201d The Dabuyid dynasty effectively resisted this process for 120 years until the defeat of its ruler Khurshid. The first leader of this process refused to allow those affected to adopt kuniyat, reflecting their status as most common targets of the pejorative \u2018ajam. That leader was later assassinated by (*) Piruz Nahavandi who had been made a slave as a result of this process. The library of the capital of the polity targeted by this process was destroyed for its contents either being contrary to, or redundant because of, the Qur\u2019an; that capital was Ctesiphon. For 10 points, what was this process that brought the former homeland of the Sassanids under the political and religious control of the Caliph?", "answer": "Muslim conquest of Persia (accept Rashidun or Arab in place of \u201cMuslim\u201d; accept Iran or Sassanids in place of \u201cPersia\u201d; accept equivalents of \u201cconquest\u201d; accept answers like Islamization of Persia as that was the long-term effect and many of the clues are about the treatment of Zoroastrians)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Attacks on the Stockade Redan by Francis P. Blair were repulsed during this campaign. A feint attack on Snyder\u2019s Bluff during this campaign aimed to divert attention away from an assault on Grand Gulf. Edward Ord replaced Corps Commander John McClernand during this campaign. In one battle in this campaign, a brigade of United States Colored Troops repulsed Henry McCulloch\u2019s attempts to cut the other side\u2019s supply lines at (*) Miliken\u2019s Bend. One commander in this campaign unsuccessfully tried to stop the other side\u2019s advance in the battles of Big Black River Bridge and Champion\u2019s Hill. Combined with Nathaniel Banks\u2019 victory at Port Hudson, victory for one side in this campaign led to the completion of the Anaconda Plan. For 10 points, name this 1863 campaign in which Ulysses Grant captured the last major Confederate stronghold on the Mississippi.\u00a0", "answer": "Siege of Vicksburg (accept the Vicksburg Campaign; Accept answers that describe the approach to or an offensive against Vicksburg)\u00a0", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A mechanical device that uses gears to keep an indicator pointing in the same direction were the \u201csouth-pointing\u201d variety of these objects. One of the six arts in the classical Confucian tradition, called yu, is specialized training in using these objects. The decisive Battle of M\u00f9y\u011b was won by Zh\u014du soldiers over disorganized Sh\u0101ng forces because of their discipline using these objects. People using these objects wielded a weapon with an axe-head on one side and a dagger on the other, called a g\u0113, to use against other people using them. During the Spring and Autumn period, groups of tightly disciplined soldiers, including archers, polearm-wielding r\u00f3ngy\u00f2u, and (*) drivers used these objects together in complex formations necessitated by their poor turning capabilities.\u00a0 For 10 points, identify these wheeled objects used with horses during the Spring and Autumn period, which were rendered obsolete across the world by the invention of the stirrup.", "answer": "chariot", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A building which was first named after the political graffiti on its exterior contains the only known artist\u2019s signature found in this place. The stylistic similarities between a statuette found at this place and the Begram Ivories have been used to provide an ante quem date for the latter. August Mau created a four-part chronological typology from the artwork of this place. The effects of an earthquake on the buildings of this place is shown in two bas-reliefs in a room dedicated to the worship of (*) lares in the home of a prominent banker. Early scholars studying this city identified many buildings as lupanares because of the prevalence of erotic frescoes. A mosaic depicting Darius III and Alexander the Great at the Battle of Issus is located in this place\u2019s House of the Faun. For 10 points, name this city, the most famous to have its art preserved in the 79 CE eruption of Mt. Vesuvius.", "answer": "Pompeii", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Cliff Fragua created a statue of one of the leaders of this conflict for the National Statuary Hall. People fleeing the conditions that prompted this conflict settled the site of El Quartelejo. Prior to this conflict, 47 religious leaders of one side were arrested, but were released in exchange for Juan Francisco Trevi\u00f1o. A leader in this conflict had his son-in-law Nicolas Bua stoned to death because of his potential sympathies for the opposing side. The start of this conflict was coordinated between its disparate participants by the distribution of (*) knotted cords, which were untied one knot per day. The establishment of encomiendas along the Rio Grande and the banning of Kachina rituals were factors prompting this conflict. Briefly freeing the namesake Native American group from Spanish rule, for 10 points, identify this 1680 conflict in New Mexico led by Pop\u00e9.", "answer": "Pueblo Revolt (accept Pop\u00e9\u2019s Rebellion before mentioned; Fragua is the first Native American artist to have his work in the National Statuary Hall)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The Inter-Allied Technical Board was responsible for administrating and revitalizing operations along this structure. John F. Stevens led the RRSC, an organization founded by the United States government to protect American goods stockpiled along this structure. One force which maintained a temporary zone of control over this structure, united with the People\u2019s Army of Komuch to capture a gold reserve at (*) Omsk. That unit, the Czechoslovak legion, maintained control of this structure until their evacuation in 1920. Sergei Witte oversaw construction of this structure, which saw its completion with the construction of the Khabarovsk Bridge in 1916. For 10 points, name this transcontinental railway network used to transport goods and people that stretches from Moscow to Vladivostok.", "answer": "Trans-Siberian railway (accept: Trans-Siberian railroad)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A man with this surname is the namesake of the most famous \u201cgrease trail\u201d, which connects Quesnel and Bella Coola. A man with this surname collected the library at Fort Chipewyan, leading to it being called \u201cthe little Athens of the Arctic regions.\u201d This is the surname of the man who replaced fellow Beaver Club member Peter Pond in his highest post after Pond was acquitted of killing John Ross. A man with this surname established Fort Fork and is the unofficial namesake of the (*) XY Company, a short-lived competitor of the North West Company. This is the surname of an explorer most famous for following the course of the Disappointment River to the Arctic Ocean. For 10 points, give this surname held by the first person to cross North America north of Mexico, the namesake of the longest river in Canada.", "answer": "Mackenzie (accept Alexander Mackenzie or Roderick Mackenzie)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One source claims that before a migration, seven leaders of this people chose the son of \u00dcgyek to lead them, sealing their decision by mingling their blood in one container. According to the Chronicum Pictum, this people procured land from Zuataplug by exchanging a white horse with a gilded saddle. After a series of raids made by this people into his territory, Louis the Child killed their leader Kursz\u00e1n during a feigned negotiation. One of this people, Emese, dreamt that she was impregnated by (*) Turul, a mythical bird, foretelling that her son \u00c1lmos would lead this people to a new land. It is uncertain whether one leader of the honfoglal\u00e1s (\u201cHONE\u201d-fohg-lah-lahsh) of this people held the title of kende or gyula. For 10 points, who is this people whose first royal dynasty was founded by \u00c1rp\u00e1d?", "answer": "Magyars (accept Hungarians)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An Incubus song references this year in the first line of its chorus before asking \u201cWhat are you waiting for, a certain shade of green?\u201d. The writings of Daniel Pinchbeck form the basis of an environmentalist documentary directed by Jo\u00e3o Amorim partially titled for this year. A trio of beings throw the Eiffel Tower into the Houses of Parliament and make the heads on Mt. Rushmore kiss in a Treehouse of Horror segment set in this year. Serbia\u2019s Mt. Rtanj (ruh-TAHN) received a spike in tourism in this year, as some people believed that it contained a (*) bunker built by aliens. A Nostradamus prediction about a \u201cdancing horse\u201d and nine circles led some to theorize that \u201cGangnam Style\u201d reaching one billion YouTube views would signal the end of time. For 10 points, the arrival of the thirteenth b\u2019ak\u2019tun was popularly believed to herald the end of the world in which Gregorian year?", "answer": "2012 CE", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A 1995 government Terms of Reference critiqued this doctrine for its assumption of completely rational behavior from all actors. This doctrine was challenged by the Dead Hand system, which allowed one state to act on it without waiting for approval. One state acted on this doctrine with Operation Chrome, which ended after a plane crash near Thule Air Base. Despite a promise made at the (*) Reykjavik Summit to share it, many criticized SDI for disturbing the viability of this doctrine. This doctrine became fully realizable for the US with the creation of the Convair B-36 \u201cPeacemaker\u201d, which was soon joined by ICBMs as a delivery method for the central objects of this doctrine. For 10 points, name this Cold War geopolitical deterrence doctrine that drove the nuclear arms race between the US and the Soviet Union.", "answer": "mutually assured destruction (accept MAD either said as one word or spelled; accept deterrence until the beginning of second clue, then prompt before mentioned)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A revolutionary group in this modern-day country was led by seven \u201cpromoters\u201d who expounded six main principles, including universal education. The Don Muang aerodrome was occupied during the Boworadet rebellion in this country. A government in this country was disgraced after it attempted to corner the lumber market and mismanaged a famine in Isan, leading to a 1957 coup. A group known as the \u201cPeople\u2019s Party\u201d forced this country\u2019s monarch to accept a (*) constitution in 1932. A capital originally known as Rattanakosin was established in this modern-day country, and the founder of that capital executed the founder of the Thonburi Kingdom, Taksin. Before dying in 2016, a ruler of this country, Bhumibol, ruled for seventy years. For 10 points, which country is home to the Chakri Dynasty, who rule from Bangkok?\u00a0", "answer": "Thailand", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A president of one of these organizations, Emile Vandervelde, proposed the Charter of Quaregnon. An organization by this name adapted the Transitional Programme and was once headed by the Belgian Ernest Mandel. Harriet Law sat on one of these organization\u2019s general councils, and delegates excluded from that organization\u2019s Hague Congress formed the Congress of St. Imier. The first of these events was held in St. Martin\u2019s Hall in (*) London in 1864, while the second was founded in Paris in 1889, excluded Anarchists, and, in honor of the Haymarket Affair, fixed May 1 as Labor Day. The third of these was formed in Moscow in 1919, and Vladimir Tatlin designed a \u201cmonument to\u201d that organization. For 10 points, name these 19th and 20th-century gatherings of socialist and communist parties that featured representatives from multiple countries.\u00a0", "answer": "Internationals (accept any numbered International such as the Second International; accept the International Workingman\u2019s Association; accept IWA; accept Comintern; accept FI)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This kingdom\u2019s incredibly rare first stamps are known as \u201cMissionary Stamps\u201d as most extant ones have survived due to the correspondence of missionaries. A minister of this kingdom who named himself after William Pitt the Younger suppressed a rebellion against the government\u2019s rejection of native beliefs. The investigations by Irish monks Columba Murphy and Arsenius Walsh and pressure from French officer Cyrille Laplace led to the reversal of eight years of Catholic persecution in this kingdom. The \u2018Ai Noa, or (*) \u201cfree eating\u201d, began when a new ruler of this kingdom ate a meal with his late father\u2019s wives and ended official support of the traditional kapu beliefs. This kingdom\u2019s Reform Party was largely composed of the descendants of missionaries and was important in forcing the adoption of the Bayonet Constitution. For 10 points, name this kingdom, the natives gods of which include K\u016b, Lono, and Pele.", "answer": "Kingdom of Hawai\u2019i", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A 1972 book by Walter Burkert applied the then-dominant theory of the paleoanthropological importance of this practice to ancient Greek religion. The arthritis displayed in the right elbow of the Mungo Man remains from Australia are consistent with the use of a woomera, an object used in this practice. Eight objects found at Sch\u00f6ningen, Germany were used for this practice by Homo heidelbergensis. Abnormal australopithecine crania in contexts with herbivore bones, but not stone tools, led to an \u201costeodontokeratic\u201d culture for engaging in this practice to be proposed by (*) Raymond Dart. Henri Breuil\u2019s study of cave art led him to hypothesize that paintings of animals were created as a type of \u201cmagic\u201d to ensure the success of this practice. For 10 points, what is this practice ancient humans performed on animals like wooly rhinos and mammoths for their skins, bones, and meat?", "answer": "hunting (prompt on \u201ckilling\u201d or \u201cviolence\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A small military unit made up of soldiers from several Commonwealth countries called the Dunsterforce disbanded after losing a battle for a city that is predominantly this ethnicity. After World War II, a communist leader of this non-Kurdish ethnicity established a short-lived \u201cPeople\u2019s Government\u201d breakaway state that ended in 1946 when Stalin removed the Red Army from their territory. Most of the victims of the (*) March Days massacres were of this ethnicity committed by Dashnaks and Bolsheviks, which was reprised in the September Days massacres. After the treaty of Turkmenchay, the Talysh people and people of this ethnicity became split between two empires after a border moved to the Aras River. After the fall of the Soviet Union, this ethnicity\u2019s home country lost a war over a region that is home to the unrecorgnized Republic of Artsakh. For 10 points, name this Turkic ethnic group who have fought three wars over Nagorno-Karabakh with Armenia.", "answer": "Azerbaijanis (accept Azeris)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A secessionist movement in this country developed out of a famine relief team before seizing telephone infrastructure and declaring- independence in a brief conflict in 1966. A 1975 treaty signed by this country\u2019s government and by representatives of Zashei Huire, criticized for not involving the leader of one nationalist movement named Phizo, was signed in the town of Shillong. A militant group in this country was founded in the Rang Ghar, a building dating back to the (*) Ahom Kingdom in one of this country\u2019s valleys. This country\u2019s government passed the AFSPA Act in 1958, which gave its military special powers to promote public order in designated \u201cdisturbed areas\u201d. Militant groups in this country\u2019s northeast have advocated for independence for the tribal minority groups in its Seven Sisterly States. For 10 points, identify this country, which for decades has faced insurgencies agitating for the independence of Nagaland, Manipur, and Assam.", "answer": "India", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Historian James Laver applied the concept of zeitgeist to the study of this industry\u2019s history, and conceptualized a 160-year cycle that its products go through because he thought time had eclipsed place in importance. Until fleeing to London after the French Revolution, Rose Bertin was an incredibly influential figure in this industry, and used berlines in trips she took to promote her products. While they were first produced by the Mercure Galant, after the French Revolution many magazines promoted new products of this industry with highly detailed drawings and lithographs called this industry (*) plates. In the 1920s, products in this industry intended for women unusually converged with products for men, and were associated with a subculture that listened and danced to jazz music. The often politically radical faction during the French Revolution called the Sans-culottes were named for their lack of access to expensive products of this industry. For 10 points, identify this industry, traditionally dominated by French men and women organized into houses.", "answer": "fashion (accept clothing, apparel, costume, or other answer indicating the making of what people wear)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A monk named Bahrey is an important, but culturally biased, source of information about the early history of this people. Historically, this people elected a \u201cfather of the scepter\u201d to important public offices, who would serve a maximum of eight years. As part of a complicated social system, the men of this people were organized into five groups called miseensa as part of the practice of gadaa. Under Bifol\u00e9, this people made the inhabitants of areas they conquered into serfs called gebrs, and under Mesl\u00e9 they improved their military strength by adopting horses. The most powerful men during the (*) Zemene Mesafint period were leaders of this people. The expansion of this pagan people into highlands occupied by Harari and Amharic peoples occurred shortly after a long war between the Adal Sultanate and the Christian Solomonic dynasty. For 10 points, identify this African people, who expanded into northern Kenya and central Ethiopia in the 16th century.", "answer": "Oromo (accept Borana Oromo)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A governor of this state defended attacks against his plans to develop one region by producing an elevation map and saying \u201cWater will run downhill\u201d. In what may be the largest land purchase ever made by an individual, Hamilton Disston bought 4 million acres in this state in 1881. To prevent speculation, one company created dummy corporations like the Ayefour Corporation to buy land for a project in this state. Aladdin City was one of several planned towns that failed due to the (*) popping of a real estate bubble in this state in the 1920\u2019s. Though allowing for the expansion of ranching and sugar production, altering the flow of the Kissimmee River did not drain this state\u2019s largest lake as planned. Managing the waters of Lake Okeechobee and the Everglades were among concerns for developing, for 10 points, which US state?", "answer": "Florida", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A poem written during the period of Viking raids of this region declares its author \u201cfear[s] not the coursing of a clear sea by... fierce heroes.\u201d It remains uncertain what sources from this region meant in labelling Viking groups as \u201cblack foreigners\u201d or \u201cwhite foreigners\u201d. Turgesius was the first Viking to conquer significant portions of this region and established a longphort [\u201clong-port\u201d] near the settlement of (*) \u00c1th Cliath. Recent archaeological findings have confirmed medieval accounts of monks from this region settling in Iceland before the Vikings. Though it resulted in his death, Viking power in this region was broken by Brian Boru at the Battle of Clontarf. For 10 points, name this region, which saw the growth of settlements like Limerick and Dublin into significant trading towns under Viking control.", "answer": "Ireland (accept \u00c9ire)", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}